[Music]
Welcome to new busy central launch
edition 2025 release wave 2. Today we
will try to explain what is new about
APIs in e documents. This is antibiotic
plant and now finally this is live. So
my name is Alexander Totovich as a
product manager for this functionality
and I have my colleague with me today.
>> Hi my name is Manos and I'm one of the
engineers for this feature. Thank you
Magnus. So let's see why we actually
deliver this functionality as
functionality technical feature in a
busy central. So first we wanted to
enable flexible and codefree
integration. What does it mean? It
doesn't mean that it should be first
channel of communication. It can be but
this is not intended for that. This is
much for to make some parallel or
additional channel communication in the
case that you want to make some specific
situation to send through some for
example to upload to one drive for
specific customer or shareepoint and not
to code for all these channel of
communication because probably you will
send to purple network but you want for
specific customer to do something to
deliver some specific way. So you can
use easily power automate or some other
similar tools. No code required. So you
can make full flow to do whatever you
want with your e documents and you can
use in another directions as well. So it
will definitely enhance accessibility
collaboration. It breaking all
boundaries uh related to e documents
communication because we will general
deliver some of channels communication
but you can do much more with external
sources without any problem. And the
last but not the least definitely it
enable your usage and creation of new
custom agent using copilot studio
because now this is available with APIs
you can easily use with copilot studio
and orchestrate with your custom agents.
So this is probably one of the
additional most important reasons. So
what do we have inside? You can use e
documents as a trigger for the
processes. So you can orchestrate
additional alternative flows. So
whatever you you want as explained
sharepoint one drive now I'm trying to
imagine some other sources so you can do
everything what is not part of the
business center or just sending email
different way because maybe you do not
use uh um Microsoft H65 so you can use
some another mail uh channel so this is
on you you can easily set up this in a
power automate or some other similar
tool and on other side as I said you can
use you can generate e documents from
external sources So you can receive PoE
or some other XML specific XML pro
format not maybe only PoE some different
we do not support and you can easily
generate new e documents in a system
based on this external uh information
and from various different channels. So
what is inside? We deliver five APIs and
two business events. So I will not read
all of them. You can see them on the
screen and I will switch to my colleague
Magnus to show you how it works in a
practice.
>> Yes. Yeah. So I thought that uh to
actually show like these uh new APIs,
let's actually do some some demos in
Power Automate where we already have uh
business central actions that we can use
out of the box with these. Um
so the first one we'll start with is
actually setting up a uh SharePoint. So
whenever you put a file on a SharePoint,
we will create an e document in uh
business central. Um so let's see how we
can do that. I have set up this uh
SharePoint folder and I will just say
select upload here and select files and
then I will choose this demo XML
like so. And now before it actually gets
to to business, let's just take a look
at the flow that I created. So then we
can also inspect the the APIs. And I
have one here that's called create a
document from SharePoint. So let's open
it.
And as you can see here, the first two
actions are um actually default
SharePoint actions of just when a file
is created, we just get the file
contents. I read that into a variable in
Power Automate. Important to note is
that we expect the contents of a of an
electronic document in B 64. So you can
see here that I'm using B 64 of the file
contents before I am using the business
central standard action create a record.
I have uh put my environment in and I'm
using the API category when Microsoft e
document version one and here we have
the new e documents um table that you
can select
and then it's just filling in the
parameters. These are all automatically
loaded by power automate. It's like
super handy and smart, very easy to use.
You just put in one in document entry
number. Then you have to select a
service that exists in your system. So I
have chosen e documents because I have
that on my demo tenant. Then the file
contents and a name for the file and
then I want to process it whenever if we
actually receive it into BC. Here you
could also say no and then it would just
be put in BC and you would have to
manually go and do that. Uh let's
actually before we jump into BC, let's
see if we can see that the flow was run
because that would be good.
So we have a history here and we see
that 18 seconds ago this flow was
actually successfully run. And if I go
to BC now and navigate to inbound e
documents,
we should have a yes, the latest
document that was received at 316
that is actually processed. You can see
that is it's the processing status is
processed and the document type is
purchase invoice and there is actually
also a finalized invoice that I can go
uh directly to. So in this I'll just
skip over the document completely and go
into the purchase invoice that we now
have in the system that have been read
with uh a desk and is it two chairs I
think it is two chairs. Yes. So that is
an example of setting using power
automate to actually this as the source
um getting a file from a sharepoint for
instance it could be one drive whatever
you desire and then um hooking it up to
creating a a e document in business
central. The second flow I wanted to
show is when we sent right so we have a
business event that happens whenever an
e document service status changes. So I
will go here and just go to one of our
customers and I just have a default e
document uh sending profile set up and I
will just create a sales invoice.
So I will put a reference number here
and then I will put I will take a desk
here
and I'll just post it
and that is good. We can go to the e
document and we can see that this one is
actually not connected to any
integration. So the document is just
exported inside of BC. Um but I have
used the flow that I created to actually
get it out of BC. So let's go back to my
flows here. We'll take the one that is
called get e document from a business
event and we can just edit that so we
can see what actually goes on. And this
is one of these business events that we
have added that's called e document
service status changed. You get the data
back. You just pass it with the JSON as
I did here. And then you can see that
the condition I have set is that the e
document service status has to be
exported for us to actually move
forward. So in any other case for
instance where you're importing stuff
this flow would not actually trigger um
sending an email. Then I did all of the
APIs we added just so we see all of
them. The first one is just to get an e
document and here you can use the e
document ID that we got by passing the
JSON when this business event was run.
And here you can use the E documents
table and that would just give you the
raw data or the fields back from from
the E document. Then you can use the get
E document service. In this case, I'm
using also the E document service ID I
got back from the business event. And
that will give me all the information we
have on the E document service. Then you
can find the specific service status. So
that's a combination of both the E
document and the service.
So as you can see here, this is a little
bit more complicated, but in essence,
I'm using an O data filter query to set
up that the E document entry number here
has to be equal to the E document entry
number and that E document service code
has to be equal to the yeah the code or
the the service code. Good. So then you
run that query that will give you that
specific E document service status.
And then finally we can actually get the
file contents as well. So we have this
API that is called e document file
content. And here you can see that I
actually set the filters for the e
document entry number using exactly the
same as I did before. Just you can also
do it this way in power automate for the
e document service code and the entry
number. That will then run. And then
once that has run, we have to call a
more direct path which is e document
filecontent /filecontent where we get
back a service or system ID. We get that
back from the first instance we ran
here. So that will return me a system ID
of this specific content and then I'm
just calling the action get an image
file or document with this system ID and
that returns me uh the the contents and
then I set up to connect to my email
account here and just says here and is
an invoice and then I decode the B 64 I
get back from from the action. So while
I have been talking I I've also received
an email and as you can see here the
this demo invoice it says here is an
invoice and in the attachment is this
XML where you can then we can just open
it up and you can see that this is
pebble that was exported inside of
business central. So there is many
options of course I just chose to send
it as email as that's very easy to
illustrate but you could hook it up to
whatever is uh possible in in uh power
automate.
That's it for for demonstrating the the
APIs.
>> Thank you, Magus.
So, you can play with that. You can see
what you can achieve with different
options. And uh now before closing this
session, please look find some of these
general resources for Business Central,
six different interesting sources for
resources. And then do not forget to
subscribe to our LinkedIn profile to
check all our new weekly news and
announcements so on. And do not forget
to watch more videos. Not only this one,
we will have three four additional uh
videos for e documents, what is new in
this release, but also you can find uh
what is uh new related to other
functionalities and previous editions.
So please go there aksbu YouTube. Thank
you for watching this video.